Catherine Seelye Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Catherine Seelye Papers.
undated, 1917-1978 [bulk 1973-1976].
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Seelye, Catherine.
1.5 linear feet.
Research notes, correspondence, and transcriptions for Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths (NY: Grossman, 1975), edited by Catherine Seelye. Seelye was a librarian at the University of Connecticut, which holds the Charles Olson Papers. Her edited book reproduces notes, essays, and poems Olson wrote during his frequent visits with Ezra Pound at St. Elizabeths Hospital in Washington, D.C., after Pound was declared mentally unfit to stand trial for treason in 1945. The collection includes correspondence from prominent literary figures in American poetry and the Black Mountain School. Donald Allen, Edward Dahlberg, Robert Duncan, James Laughlin, and Omar Pound are among those represented. Professional ethics in the archival and publishing fields are also addressed.
MSS19980211
Biography
From 1960-1974, Catherine Seelye worked in the library of the University of Connecticut, first in Collection Development and later as Assistant Librarian. Her husband, John Seelye, was an English Professor also at the University of Connecticut. When the University purchased the Charles Olson Papers in 1972, John and Catherine Seelye developed a proposal to edit and publish Olson's reflections on Ezra Pound. (Olson had intended to publish the materials himself after Pound's death, but Olson's death in 1970 preceded Pound's in 1972.)
Once the publication was approved, Catherine Seelye took on the task of transcribing and editing Olson's material in collaboration with the curator of the Charles Olson Papers, George Butterick. By the time Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths was published in 1975, Catherine Seelye and her husband had moved to North Carolina. Seelye kept in correspondence with Butterick about extending the project to include the rest of Olson's notebooks, but their plans never reached fruition.
Catherine Seelye received her B.A. from West Virginia University and M.A. from University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. As a librarian for the Institute of Government at the University of North Carolina from 1955-1960, Seelye indexed and edited Popular Government and other publications. During her years at the University of Connecticut, she wrote articles for various library bulletins. Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths remained her only published book.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the supporting material gathered and generated by Catherine Seelye while preparing Charles Olson's reflections on Ezra Pound for publication. The bulk of material dates from 1973-1976. It includes Seelye's correspondence with prominent literary figures such as Donald Allen, Charles Boer, Edward Dahlberg, Robert Duncan, Donald Gallup, James Laughlin. Other correspondents include Pound's son, Omar Pound, and Olson's widow, Constance (Olson) Bunker. Copies of Olson's work and correspondence are also included, the originals of which are in the Charles Olson Papers at the University of Connecticut. The inclusive dates for the collection reflect the dating of the originals.
Throughout the collection there is an ongoing discussion of copyright and libel concerns. Professional ethics in the archival and publishing fields is also addressed. Particularly notable is John Seelye's correspondence (Series I: Correspondence) proposing the project and the exchange regarding the publication of Robert von Hallberg's article on Olson's poem "Issue, Mood" (Series II: Subject Files). Seelye strenuously objected to von Hallberg's interpretation of Olson's poem and his extensive use of the collection's previously unpublished material with which she also was working.
Organization
Series I: Correspondence (1966-1978) Incoming and outgoing correspondence ordered alphabetically by individual. Exceptions: John Seelye's correspondence and general responses to publication appear first.
Series II: Subject Files (1917-1975) Subject files containing background research on Olson and Pound.
Series III: Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths (1973-1976) Publication materials, drafts and reviews.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Charles Olson and his interests. See especially the Papers of Charles Olson and George Butterick (partially processed). The published book, Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths (Dodd C2821), is also held in the archives.
Other literary collections in Archives & Special Collections contain additional materials on many of the American literary figures represented in this collection, including Black Mountain poets.
For detailed information on any of these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject with original order maintained as closely as possible. Correspondence has been ordered chronologically. If applicable, Seelye's notes of questions or an article by the correspondent are included in the correspondence folder. Duplicate copies of articles and reviews have been removed.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Seelye, Catherine.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.
Subjects:
Allen, Donald Merriam, 1912- --Correspondence.; Laughlin, James, 1914- --Correspondence.; Pound, Omar S.--Correspondence.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.; Saint Elizabeths Hospital (Washington, D.C.); Poets, American--20th century.; American literature--20th century.; Psychiatric hospital patients--Washington (D.C.); Psychiatric hospitals--Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.)--Medical affairs--Hopsitals, sanatoriums, etc.; Essays.; Women editors--United States.; Editors--United States.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Press releases.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Obituaries.; Newspapers.; Essays.
Occupations:
Author.; Editor.; Librarian.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, 1966-1978
  - John Seelye's correspondence (4), 1966-1976 (Box 1:1)
  - Responses to publication (4), 1975-1977 (Box 1:2)
  - Allen, Donald M. (4), 1974 (Box 1:3)
  - Boer, Charles (2), 1975 (Box 1:4)
  - Bunker, Constance (6), 1974 (Box 1:5)
  - Burkhart, Charles (1), 1973-1974 (Box 1:6)
  - Butterick, George (17), 1974-1978 (Box 1:7)
  - Cech, John (8), 1973-1974 (Box 1:8)
  - Cowley, Malcolm (1), 1974 (Box 1:9)
  - Cranston, Alan (1), 1973 (Box 1:10)
  - Dahlberg, Edward (2), 1974 (Box 1:11)
  - Drummond, John (1), 1974 (Box 1:12)
  - du Sautoy, Peter / Faber & Faber (2), 1974 (Box 1:13)
  - Duncan, Robert (1), 1975 (Box 1:14)
  - Gallup, Donald / Yale University Library (7), 1973-1975 (Box 1:15)
  - Gill, Howard (1), 1973-1974 (Box 1:16)
  - Grossman Publishers / Viking Publishers (19), 1974-1976 (Box 1:17)
  - Heymann, C. David (3), 1974 (Box 1:18)
  - Kavka, Jerome Dr. (3), 1973-1975 (Box 1:19)
  - Kenner, Hugh (1), 1973 (Box 1:20)
  - Laughlin, James / New Directions Press (12), 1974-1975 (Box 1:21)
  - Litz, Walton (1), 1973 (Box 1:22)
  - Meacham, Harry (2), 1973-1974 (Box 1:24)
  - Moore, Frank (2), 1974 (Box 1:25)
  - Paideum (2), 1973-1974 (Box 1:26)
  - Pound, Omar (3), 1974-1976 (Box 1:27)
  - St. Elizabeths Hospital (2), 1973-1974 (Box 1:28)
  - Stimpson, Catherine (1), 1973 (Box 1:29)
  - Stock, Noel (2), 1974-1975 (Box 1:30)
  - Stoddard, Roger / Houghton Library (1), 1974 (Box 1:31)
  - United States Government (4), 1973 (Box 1:32)
  - Weeks, Edward (2), 1973-1975 (Box 1:33)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1917-1975
  - Arioste Research, 1974 (Box 1:34)
  - "Axe Tree Sun" by Olson (copy), [c.1945] (Box 1:35)
  - Boston-Herald Pound's Letter to Editor, 1939 (Box 1:36)
  - Capital Daily, 1973 (Box 1:37)
  - "Capital Stuff" in Times-Herald, 1945 (Box 1:38)
  - Creeley, Robert Letters to Olson (copy), 1950 (Box 1:39)
  - Dalton Research, undated (Box 1:40)
  - Elliot, T.S. Letter to Olson (copy), 1946 (Box 1:41)
  - Faust Buch #1 by Olson (copy), 1947 (Box 2:42)
  - Faust Buch #1 Transcription and Notes, 1974 (Box 2:43)
  - Ford, Ford Maddox, Preface, 1917 (Box 2:44)
  - Fox, Douglas Letters to Olson (copy), 1946-1947 (Box 2:45)
  - Frank, Lewis Jr. Letters to Olson (copy), 1946 (Box 2:46)
  - Freedom and Plenty Research, 1974 (Box 2:47)
  - Frobenius, Leo NUC Listings, undated (Box 2:48)
  - Gesell Research (some German), 1954-1965 (Box 2:49)
  - Glover, Albert Diss. Olson Biography, 1968 (Box 2:50)
  - Greenburg Notes, undated (Box 2:51)
  - Kaspur Notes, undated (Box 2:52)
  - Library Book Listings, 1974 (Box 2:53)
  - Mood Research, 1973 (Box 2:54)
  - New Age Research, 1973 (Box 2:55)
  - New English Weekly Pound Letter to Editor, 1938 (Box 2:56)
  - Newsweek Articles on Pound, 1945 (Box 2:57)
  - Olson Background, undated (Box 2:58)
  - Olson Biographical Data, undated (Box 2:59)
  - Olson's Notebook (copy) and Seelye's Notes, 1945-1973 (Box 2:60)
  - Olson's Notebook (copy), 1948 (Box 2:61)
  - Olson Photographs (copy), 1948 (Box 2:62)
  - Poetry Pound's Cantos, 1917 (Box 2:63)
  - Pound Background, Articles and Obituaries, 1938-1973 (Box 2:64)
  - Unanswered Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2:65)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch Article on Pound, 1939 (Box 2:66)
  - von Hallberg, Robert Article and Internal Memos, 1973 (Box 2:67)
  - Washington Cathedral re: Proctor Research, 1973-1974 (Box 2:68)
- Series III: Charles Olson and Ezra Pound: An Encounter at St. Elizabeths, 1973-1976
  - Research Foundation Grant from University of Connecticut, 1973 (Box 2:69)
  - Permissions, [c.1974?] (Box 2:70)
  - Title Page, Contents, Acknowledgements, [c.1973-1974] (Box 2:71)
  - Introduction, [c.1973-1974] (Box 2:72)
  - Lustrum For You, EP, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:73)
  - Your Witness, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:74)
  - Fragments, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:75)
  - Canto 1, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:76)
  - Canto 2, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:77)
  - Canto 3, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:78)
  - Canto 4, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:79)
  - Canto 5, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:80)
  - Canto 6, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:81)
  - Canto 7, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:82)
  - Canto 8, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:83)
  - Canto 9, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:84)
  - Canto 10, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:85)
  - Grandpa, Goodbye, [c.1973-1974] (Box 3:86)
  - Corrected Manuscript, [c.1974] (Box 3:87-88)
  - Copy-edited Manuscript, [c.1974] (Box 3:89-90)
  - Galley Proof, 1975 (Box 3:91)
  - Promotional Materials, 1975 (Box 3:92)
  - Reviews, 1975-1976 (Box 3:93)